for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations
and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him.
And they will praise and bless and celebrate with song
the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge
but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons and saints.
In our time, many year into break
of the prison of a flat, secular materialism,
to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen De Young,
host this live Colin show,
focused on enchantment in creation.
The union of the scene and unseen as made by God
and experienced by mankind.
history. Welcome to the Lord of
spirits. Greetings, Starfighters.
You have been recruited by the
Star League to defend the frontier
against Zuer and the code in our
moda. You're listening to the
you just you just let a fuse.
Really? Yes, we're now going to
get a horrible remake slash
legacy sequel. Even to the
Cobra Kai audience.
Hmm. And that dizzy is going
to hear about it. They're going to
remake flight of the Navigator.
be some kind of like
I think AI version of Robert Preston,
that'll be probably, probably,
or they'll get an actor in the
doose of digital face thing.
Yep.
What have you done?
Well, I mean, this is what you get
when you listen to the 129th episode
of the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Nevertheless, I am Father Andrew Steven Damick,
and with me is Professor and Confessor
to the stars, Father Steven D. Young,
and we are alive.
Start it.
in the second half of the show. If you are joining us live, you can call us at 855-237-2346.
And if you make it past the great gatekeeper, Mike, Prince Albert, and it can't again,
you can talk directly to us. It's been exactly 120 episodes since our far-famed installment
taught by a star to worship the Son of Righteousness back in the long ago days of your in 2020.
So that means that by sheer numerological force, it is required that we finally do a full
episode dedicated to astrology.
So, Father, when we said we're going to come back to this, we're going to come back always keep our promises.
In a multiple of 12.
So, I have a question to start off, Father.
And I didn't put this in the script because I didn't want you to have any chance to prepare on this one.
Like I would anyway.
But yeah, go ahead.
Like I read your script.
Tough foot fair.
So, you know, before, long before you ever met your wife through World of War...
or craft, which for those of you out there, that is true.
Did anyone ever attempts to ask you on a date by asking you, what's your sign?
No.
I am a decade too young for that.
That's true.
I know I read older than I am, but that was that was what was a lot of
How do you feel about the curiosity since this is going around a lot lately?
What did your Spotify rap to give you?
listening ages. I have no idea because I don't listen to music on Spotify. Oh okay. All vinyl. No.
I actually, I am the guy who shells out for YouTube premium so I don't have to watch ads.
Which gives me access to YouTube music. You're the one. I'm the guy who does that. Yeah,
And let me just tell you, okay, some of you kids out there
If you haven't already, you're going to decide, hey, I want to make a reaction channel.
I of course cannot make a reaction channel because I have seen all the movies and all the TV shows
that hurt all the music. But some of you out there, many of you have not. And so you may say,
I'm going to start a reaction channel. If you're going to react to things on YouTube in your own YouTube
videos, you need to pay for YouTube premium. Why? You do not need to be skipping ads while you're
reacting to videos.
That's...
That's true. That's true. That is amateur nonsense. Did he literally watch them skipping ads? Because I don't want to. Yes.
In videos. Yes. Yes. I have seen this low red nonsense. Okay. Like you got to invest a little bit of infrastructure if you're starting your own channel.
The what 12 or 15 bucks a month that won't kill you. All the kids out there feeling very chastised right now.
You're saying so.
Yeah.
But anyway, so I got a...
YouTube year and wrap up that included all the music I listened to but did not have a listening
age listening age. Yeah. Sound off in the chat everybody. What are you listening ages. Although
the algorithm. Roll it told me his was like 68 or something like that. Whereas mine was
30 because of as we know my new found new found love for K-pop. Yeah, I thought yours was
going to be 13 year old girl.
But, you know, hey, I guess you want to do something else too.
Yeah, it balances out.
Yeah, it was that and like, you know early medieval English, you know, maddening or something. I mean, I do love a good loot. Yeah, the one eerie thing about my YouTube wrap up is that at the end, it gives you like a cryptic horse. See, I'm bringing us back on topic horoscope.
scope-esque.
You're bringing us back on topic.
Like, I know how the worm has turned.
But fortune cookie like saying about you, right?
And mine was eerily correct.
It said that I was the person in any group most likely to make an obscure movie line reference
that no one else would recognize.
Yes, that is true.
So the algorithm has warmed its way, at least partway into my blanket soul.
they know who you are.
So what is astrology, Father Stephen?
Well astrology is the logos of the stars
And I have to throw this out by the way since we brought up a little etymology
Did somebody say etymology
And I don't even have my jingle on me man. See I did you know
This just proves that it really is completely spontaneous
is, um, yeah, I mean, one of my favorite, I don't know why it's so funny.
One of my favorite etymologies that I ever learned, which weirdly took me years to actually
consider and to figure out on my own, um, is the word disaster, which is completely related
to our, our topic tonight because disaster means to be against the stars, you know,
So will this episode be a disaster or not?
with the stars. Yeah. Have you ever done the, you know, hey, did somebody say an
amology thing and they're like, no, we were talking about Beatles and
tomology and you had to just kind of go, oh, sorry. That has happened. That has
happened. I figured. I figured. Yeah, but we so we had to do the, you know, first
day of biology class, like bios, meaning life and logos, meaning the study of,
Alright, let's just say.
But in this case, I'd like say butterfly.
That does kind of work, right?
In the sense that astrology is attempting to codify,
to reason out, to put together a logos,
a discourse, a, an, an, inter-
the eternal reasoning to the movement of the stars and other heavenly objects.
And that's important because there are other similar terms.
So, right, so on one hand, there's astronomy.
Sure.
Which is a different thing.
Most people think, I think these days,
Most people think of astronomy as the science.
that has to do with the stars and you know planets and whatever else.
And astrology is this dumb superstition, you know, that they print in the newspapers.
And that occasionally, you know, the wives of presidents will consult.
Yes.
Yes. There's a good another second reference from 1984 right there.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think that's the way that most people weren't watching stranger things.
Right.
No, I have not watched stranger things.
Nope.
I was, you know, like you father, I was there.
Yes.
Yes, yes, yeah, but like a month and a half older than I am no no two and a half months older than I am yeah
No, yeah to me when stranger things was good and I've just applied that maybe it no longer is
Much to some people's consternation
It was not the nostalgia factor that was good about it. Yeah
But
Yeah, no, I the whole just playing nostalgia thing is
Well, I could go off on a whole thing about that,
on how depressing that is,
but I don't need to bring our audience down more than we already have,
and already will in this episode.
Yeah.
I mean, I think it's one of the things that a lot of folks here in 2025 may not really realize
is that the stars, we think we look up and we see a few stars, whatever.
Maybe...
a constellation or two. But most of us live in cities that's statistically true. And even
though those of us who live in more rural areas, unless you live in a truly dark area where
there's not that much lighting, you never really see the stars the way that pre-modern people
saw them. But if you've ever been in a truly dark area, like a truly dark area, and
it's a cloudless sky, and you look up and you see enough stars that you see the Milky
way for instance then you can begin the
understand why it is that ancient people looking up at this and noticing that it had these patterns
and stuff would be completely fascinated by this. You know, I mean, the stars are absolutely
a stunning thing to look at. But the sad irony is that most of us do not see them now.
Because there's too much ambient light. Yeah. There's too much ambient light. Yeah.
Unless you were to the five people in Wyoming. You made those people mad when you said that the
Let's time for the win!
I think it was Wyoming. It was Wyoming again. Okay. And they were like, Hey, don't you mean Montana? I'm pretty sure something like that. Yes, there were posts in our Facebook group about this.
Maybe if I keep stirring this up, they'll go to war. It'll be like a five on five. It's like a play basketball. A bit of a scare mission.
Yeah.
Um, to decide who was greater, uh, who was the greatest of the Great Plains States.
But yeah, so astronomy, which is of course the nomos of the stars.
When he's probably like it should be something out on, you know, what is it?
Ming's Chinese theater, those sounds very Hollywood.
Man's Chinese theater.
Man's China. That's it. Sorry. I mean, the red head would be flash Gordon's opponent.
Yes, in my head flash Gordon is still like always roll
thing. Yes. Yeah. So, but the reason for the switch in term, right, is going to become
more apparent as we go on tonight. But astronomy, right, the reason you would change it to
nomos is that by the time people started talking about astronomy, nomos had come to be translated
commonly as law and so they were distinguishing their study of
the physical laws governing the movement of stars and planets from astrology,
which as we will see was a more freewheeling discourse,
I'll say. But also, there are some sort of earlier stages of development,
right, before you get to astrology. So even if you are one of those five people in
Wyoming right and you you
outside your door on this wintry day, shovel your way out of your home and look skyward, right?
Just looking at the stars and saying, wow, that's beautiful, is not doing astrology.
No. Right, so there's also pre-astrological observations as well as in the case of the science of
astronomy what we might call post-astronomical.
or astrological observations.
And so the phenomenon that's good to be called astrology
and the place where we have the best records
about this being formed and taking shape
in the ancient world is actually in Babylon.
Surprise.
Yeah.
Chocking.
Come up a lot in this.
So we have spotty records of,
It taking shape in various different forms in other ancient Near Eastern and other ancient cultures.
But from what we can tell from those scattered pieces of evidence, it followed, of course, pretty much everywhere that's broadly similar to how this developed in Babylon.
on. So what would later become what we call astrology?
really starts with thinking about and talking about omens, not the movies, because like
after Christ returns at the end of the third one, how can you make a fourth one?
Like that's kind of the...
Let's say I swim in a certain historical question.
Yes.
ridiculous. Um,
Omen 3 by the way features Sam Neal as the Antichrist and most people may not realize how the original Omen yes had Gregory Pach in it as the father of the Antichrist and then
Three had Sam Neal playing the adult Antichrist
Wasn't Sam Neal wasn't he on
Was he the guy in red hunt for October who said I would have liked to have seen Montana see
Now it's topical again. Yes it all wraps back around. It was also Jurassic Park. Yes, yes of course.
And in the mouth of madness, which is a great horror movie by John Carpenter that's a
mishmash of H.B. Lovecraft and Stephen King. You can imagine such a thing.
If you care to imagine such a thing.
So...
But omens were talking about essentially abhorrent phenomena.
Just omens in general, right?
Are abhorrent phenomena.
Something unusual happens or is seen or is spotted.
And this unusual occurrence or appearance or happening
is then interpret it.
right make it that's what makes it an omen is that
some interpretation, some importance is a scribe to it.
You just see something weird and go,
and walk away, it's not really an omen, right?
But if you see something weird and you go,
what does that mean?
What was that all about?
That was a sign of something.
Now it's an omen, okay?
And so we've talked before on the show about ex-dispacy,
ex-dispacy which is performed by your local horror spec
and involves looking at the entrails of sacrificial animals.
And we've talked about how, you know, they would spot certain things like,
oh, there's a spot on this part of the liver, or on this part of the right kidney
that isn't normal for a sheep or a goat or a bull or whatever was being sacrificed or a pig.
And so that would then be seen as a sign of something.
Same thing is
through of things happening in the heavens.
So real obvious ones are like solar and lunar eclipses,
right? Those are not normal. They don't have a lot of time.
Everybody knows that, not just the star nerds.
Yeah. But then also things like comments, shooting stars,
other things like this, right? Would occasionally be seen by someone.
and because they were abnormal, right, some significant.
against was described to them.
And we know that this kind of thing was happening
in a semi-organized way within Babylonian religion,
as far back as the 19th century BC,
because we have an accadian text from that time
that just catalogs a ton of omens.
Like, it's just a long list of weird things
and what they mean.
And
It's a mix of, this text is a mix of things related to ex-Mrs. P, which is why I brought it up as an example.
So things you'll see in entrails and things you'll see in the sky.
Right. And it's just a long, long list, catalog.
And this means, you know, there's going to be a bad harvest.
to this means there's going to be war.
This means you should...
move in, you know, the people should move in this direction or that direction.
This means that you need to store up extra for the winter, et cetera, et cetera, on and
on and on. Right. This leads just going to be wild animals attacking your livestock.
But so the importance of the text is not just that, oh, yeah, people were doing this then,
because we know people were doing it.
But that they compiled such a text,
implies that they were doing it in an organized way,
that there was some kind of literate priesthood
who was assigned with compiling this list
and then interpreting omens when they happened
for the culture.
So this is an embedded cultural thing by that point.
It was seen as
just something you do, right? Like, you know, checking your, I was about to say checking
your voice mail, but I don't, kids these days probably don't do that anymore.
Now they feel offended if you actually call them on the phone.
Looking at your skibbity raise on the tweet talks or whatever your kids do.
I'm supposed to mention six, seven or I don't even know.
Yeah, like, does anyone know what that thing is?
I think what it means is that it doesn't mean anything.
No, I can totally explain that to you,
but I'm not going to do that now.
That's fine.
Because that would be too big of a regression,
even for this show.
But yeah, it has to do with rap music
and basketball, two of your favorite things.
Hmm.
I mean, a lot of my ethnic countrymen play the basketballs.
Yes.
You're not so much. So you're tall enough.
Well, I'm sure that because I'm tall, I could play basketball. And it's like, I had back problems as a teenager. So I did I used to play basketball, but I stopped.
So there you go. A little bit of the history of me.
Yeah, I was I was pretty much right out unless they did professional horse. We've got a professional horse.
Maybe I can get it.
Okay.
I mean, it would not have...
enough time for your award-winning ballroom dancing.
Right, right. Which was, you'd think, being relatively light on my feet, you know,
that I could have done the whole but no, did not translate. Although, another fun fact,
in high school, I letered in volleyball. And I see your leather jacket. Huh?
Do you have a leather jacket, father? Yes, yeah. Wow.
I gave it to my wife.
Yeah.
Oh,
another nice reference thing.
Yeah.
But yeah,
at volleyball was invented as a game to help people practice for basketball.
So all the signs were there that I should have been good at basketball, but I was never any good at basketball.
Anyway, moving on.
I'm also not good at rapping.
which I know shocks everyone, but we'd still like recordings of that.
There probably are some. I do mic checks. I wrap on mic checks.
You've heard me do that. That is true.
But so this is our first stage in our proto-astrological discourse is...
just omens. There being a category of omens that take place in the sky,
involving the sun, moon and stars. So the next phase, and even here, we're not
really an astrology proper. But a few centuries later in Babylon, we have a more
defined system and the key thing that has changed in this system.
is that the sun and the moon and the planets, all five of them,
have been identified with particular gods.
And this stage is actually before the stage.
We've talked before on the show way back
in the ninth episode that we already mentioned
and in a couple of other episodes, like about Abraham.
And so that is it.
Of course the star...
were identified with the gods by the nations and with angelic beings,
Laura K. G. Gods in a Jewish literature, including the Old Testament and New Testament.
But this is actually before we get to the stars.
and it's the Sun Moon, the Five Planets, those Five Planets being Mercury.
the prevenous Mars Jupiter and Saturn.
Because those are the ones people could spot
with their naked eye observation.
We're pre-telescopes by millennia.
So, and so those five, the Sun and the Moon,
we can identify with gods.
And why those seven objects, well,
your some more etymology for those.
who don't know already, the word planet is a transliteration of the Greek planetes, which
means a wanderer.
Yeah.
So, as those stars, or because I mean, to the naked eye, they just look like stars.
You know, maybe big stars in some cases, but they don't follow the same kind of cyclic
paths perfectly that the rest of the stars do.
they they if you're assuming as all ancient people
did that the earth is stationary, right?
Then you have stars that sort of circle around
overhead over the course of the year.
And then you have the sun and the moon and the planets
that sort of wobble around, right, all over the place.
If you're tracking them from the perspective
of a human standing on earth.
Meaning those irregular movements,
remember what we were saying about omens?
It was the aberrant things that you notice.
Right, and so these seven objects are different than all of the other lights in the sky.
Right, the sun in the moon most obviously, but then even once you've done some more observations, these five planets, move differently than the other lights in the sky.
And so what happens is they combine this identification of those seven.
objects with the gods, with their preceding view of omens. And so now we're going to reference,
okay, here is the omens, here is the unusual thing in the sky. And that unusual thing in
this guy was related in some way to the sun or the moon or to one of the planets in
in terms of where it was in the sky or the path it took.
Right. And so then the Omen now, whatever the Omen is indicating, is going to be tied
directly to the God who they've identified with the Son or the Moon or the planet. Right.
So to get into more particulars in Mesopotamian...
proto astrology here. The sun is obviously identified with
Shammosh, right? The sun god who's
which is literally the word for sun in all of the length, all of the
Semitic languages. Yeah, or Shammam.
Right, the vowels change because it's Semitic languages, but the
consonants are the same.
And then the moon god is sin if you're a cadian or Nana, if
if you're...
Sumerian. And then the planets Jupiter Saturn, Mercury, Venus, and Mars were identified with Marduck,
Nernerda, Naboo, Ishtar, and Nurgall respectively. And if you track with that, or if you do a
little slow this down and repeat it and do a little digging, you'll find that not coincidentally,
Jupiter, Saturn, Mercury, V.
Venus and Mars, the Roman gods who we named the, who we now name those planets after,
roughly coincide with the ancient Eurystern gods who they were originally identified with.
Right like Ishtar and Venus and
Marta consumer, right, etc
And so if you see, say you spot a comment, right, at the comments tail is pointing at Jupiter, right, this was taken to be a sign of
of a Mardux comportment toward you and your civilization, right?
And then you would consult the tech.
or the priests would consult the texts to determine exactly what that meant. In terms of
disdain, he's angry, happy, peved about to take some poor human woman as a bride.
Right. What exactly is he up to? But the omen in this guy is now tied directly to a god
who has been directly connected to.
and entity in the heavens.
Yeah, which is, I mean, this is very different in a lot of ways from the way that people think
of astrology now where they're like, well, the stars and the planets, they have an influence
on your life.
This is that they're reading signals from the gods, you know, who do have an influence
in your life as far as they're concerned.
you know, these are actual spiritual beings that are present with them.
and that they're communing with and you know all that kind of stuff.
Right, right. And so the shift is right. Previously they would have said, oh,
we saw this comment. That means there's going to be famine. Now they would say, oh,
we saw this comment. Its tail was pointing at Marduk. Therefore, Marduk has mad at us that is
going to send a famine. Essentially.
Right. But so this is, we're getting closer to what we can call astrology now. Right. And we have an even more systemized text called the Anuma Anu Enlul from the 16th century BC.
So this is give or take three centuries after the previous text we mentioned.
that lays all this out in voluminous detail.
It matches up all the omens with all the celestial objects that they could be related to and what each instance means.
It's like thousands of lines of text.
So decoder ring.
So yeah, unbelievable amount of detail, right?
Yeah, so again, this
not something they just made up when they wrote that text. This is the codification of observations
and things that had been going on for centuries, for generations. Now, to get a sort of fully
devised astrological system in Babylon, we have to wait until the neo-Babolonian empire.
Because of course the Bronze Age collapse.
that sort of sets things back.
People are obviously still looking at the sky.
They're still looking at omens.
They're still doing some of these things.
But in terms of it being sort of systematized,
they're being a logo of it, right, for astrology.
That doesn't really happen again
until we get to the neo-Babalonean Empire.
And they have a fully-divided system.
And the way theirs worked is much...
you could already see.
see things that make it roughly similar to modern astrology.
For example, the stars and constellations
with their regular movement are sort of treated
like a board game board or like a map.
Right, because by this point,
they have charted out their courses
with some exactitude and were able
to make accurate predictions about the movements
of constellations and stuff, going far into the future.
Right.
And so they have all that mapped out, the regular movements of sort of the general stars
and constellations.
They have specific constellations mapped out.
They have four cardinal signs, right, four cardinal constellations.
they call cardinal consolations because they
are related to the Cardinal Directions
north-south east and west.
And I'm going to add the new year.
There are four animals.
We've mentioned this before on the show,
because the four constellations are a man, actually, a hunter.
an ox and eagle and a lion.
Yep. And probably sound very familiar to some of you, but we'll get to that.
Yes. Well, what we can touch on it here, right?
That's true. Okay. So that's all you may remember them from Ezekiel.
Yeah. Yeah.
And then also there's the whole identification of those with the four gospel writers.
I mean, you see this?
and iconography, it's very common on icons of Christ,
the great high priest, he's enthroned,
and then you see the four living creatures
and as the gospel writer, images.
So, yeah, I mean, this is astrological stuff, you guys.
Yes, and so Ezekiel sees the throne of God
on top of these four living creatures
who are angelic beings, who are constellations.
the idea is that God is enthroned above the heavens. Right? So there are the powers of the
heavens, right? These stars and planets and these beings and then God is enthroned up above them,
right? Is the idea and enthroned on them. And we say this liturgically all the time.
Christchurch seated upon or enthroned upon the cherubim. We say it all the time. That's what
that's talking about.
And so in addition to those four cardinal signs, right, there are two on either side of each of them.
So you've got 12 primary constellations.
So you've got something like a zodiac by this point, right,
in that you've got this map of the, these 12 primary constellations.
And then you have the sun, moon, and the planets, still the five planets moving through them.
You
right, wandering through them, following their own paths,
and then you have various omens showing up in various ones.
Right? And so the confluence of those relationships
is what's getting interpreted by the time you get to astrology
proper. Right?
So where is this planet right now
in relationship to what constellation.
in relationship to whenever Oman we may have seen recently, right?
All of those things get brought together.
And we also at this point have sort of fully brought to
bear Babylonian mathematics, which is what allowed them to do this so that
they're able to make accurate predictions not only about
the fixed constellations and where they'll be in the future,
but they've even charted out.
Really...
to Earth in weird squiggly lines, the paths of the planets, right? And the sun and the moon in
different seasons, right? And are able to make future predictions based on past observations.
Now, you may be wondering, well, if that's true, if they're using math,
right and they're baking prediction
and those predictions are turning out accurately, et cetera, et cetera.
Why are you saying, well, now we're an astrology instead of now we're an astronomy?
Right? Like, isn't that what astronomy does?
Is it that what all science does? Is make use past observations and mathematics
to make future predictions and check them out? Right? Like,
The difference is the key
difference here is the idea that there is a deeper spiritual meaning. Yeah, two. It's
these motions. It's not just where the stars and the planets are going to be. It's what
does that mean, especially like one way, I'm not saying this is the only way, one way of
understanding the phrase from Lord's Prayer on Earth as it isn't heaven is this idea
that
there's a reflection of in the heavens.
Yes, there's a regularity or will happen on Earth.
The stars keep their no-mose and we don't.
Right.
Keep the one that's been given to us.
Yes.
Yeah.
So yeah, it is that level of meaning that moves it into,
Let's see.
do astrology, right? And out of the realm of the science of astronomy, in the sense of modern science,
right? Because modern science, this is worth repeating a lot, modern science cannot weigh in on
meaning questions. Yeah. Modern science can tell you how things work, it can't tell you why they
work that way.
or what that means of anything or whether it's good or bad
But then that way yeah, I mean that requires at least philosophy, but probably yes, those are
Other fields other than science science can do lots of great things, right?
But it can't do that math can do lots of great things, okay, but
Math can't tell you can tell you lots of things about arose. It can't tell you why it's beautiful
You
Yeah, and so this astrological system is going beyond just, oh, hey, look, is it this cool,
we figured out how the stars move.
Right, it's gone beyond that too.
Here's why they move in this way.
And here's what it means when particular things happen.
And here's how the cycles of heavens are related to cycles on Earth that we would now say
scientific
are not strictly connected to them. Right? There's of course, you know, you can, somebody will
bring it, you know, the moon's connected to the tides. It absolutely is. But the position of
of Venus relative to Scorpio does not affect crop yields.
What?
But that's what I'm talking about when I say not directly related.
Right.
And as we all know from the incredible movie, Moonfall, the moon is hollow and fake.
Great movie.
Really?
No.
Terrible.
Let's get say.
It is ridiculous.
Yes.
ridiculous. I will just go ahead and spoil it. Like the moon starts to fall
toward the Earth. Right. So this is like ultimate disaster movie time. Right. See
there you go. Disaster see it all comes around. Yes. Ultimate disaster movie. And so
they take a space shuttle to the moon and discover it's a giant hollow alien machine.
And they have to connect to its computer and reboot the moon
to get it to go back into its place.
I just watched it as a comedy movie.
Yeah, well, no, I watched, I forget what plane flight it was.
Oh, yes.
It might be a bit more of a flu to London.
Watch.
I watched Moonfall and Morbius back to back.
Wow.
Just, you know, just flipping through alphabetically the next movie,
the next movie.
No, I just, I said, I want to find the two worst movies on this list and watch them.
And I succeeded.
both in finding the two worst movies and watching them.
So yeah, more of the way that happening looked like Shakespeare.
Like halfway through that movie, I think Matt Smith realized he was in a horrible movie.
And so they would give him like these long speeches of expository dialogue to deliver.
And he literally would just randomly start dancing for no reason in the scene,
in the scene while delivering the speech.
I think you just realized it was bad.
It was like I need to signal the audience for help.
Like I signed the contract.
I can't get out of it.
One of our colleagues in YouTube can't believe
that you didn't walk off the plane after watching that.
Yes, well, I don't buy into astrology.
I will say if the moon starts heading directly
for the earth, that is a bad sign.
And then I don't think taking a space shuttle there
reboot.
bigot will help. So the biggest place where astrology comes to bear in the ancient world
in general, not just the ancient Ereas, that we usually don't think about is the calendar.
In fact, most ancient calendars are inextricably linked to astrology.
the Julian calendar.
Even the Julian calendar created by great pagan emperor St. Julius Caesar
Decades before the birth of Christ. Yes. Nine running Sunday school. You're you're ruining a certain kind of rigorous
Catacombs. Yes.
This is for pop like the Sadducees are the ones who use the Julian calendar like
like, duh, duh, duh, duh, duh.
Yes, like, it was obviously corrupt.
people in the religious world of the first century were the woods using the
Joliet calendar.
So because the ultimate origin of the calendar is all directly related to
heavenly movements.
Right, so think about the fact that months are based on the lunar cycle.
Solar years is actually an ancient thing, right? Even even civilizations, ancient civilizations
that were on a 360 day calendar of just 12, 30 day months realized that that didn't actually
match up to the solar cycle. Sure. And so they would add days and add whole months every
years like on the Jewish calendar.
Yeah.
At the Pharisees' reason, right?
So they understood this long before even they started using necessarily solar calators.
But solar calendar was invented as we've said before, according to the Submarine Kings
list, like the Seventh King before the flood came up with the solar calendar.
They considered it ancient already.
And so this is based on the cycles of the sun.
moon. Right? And so the calendar gives structure to human life on earth. And so the calendar itself
was seen as this mediating factor between what's going on in the heavens with the gods and what's
what's going on on earth with humans.
Um...
In another five years we could do a we could do a follow-up on this and do more about calendars
There's a bunch of people in Montana right now that are
You know celebrating that you just promised five more years of the podcast. Yes. Well all five of them could throw a party for those five years
So yeah, so the cycle of feasts right the calendar was seen as itself being a sort of mediator
between the heavenly realm and
earthly realm in order to attempt to create parity. The Jewish psychophease of the Old Testament
is fundamentally different than that. But like I said, that is a topic for a distant future episode.
Yeah, so that's that sort of the short version of the development.
of astrology. And here at the end of this first half, we have something that kind of resembles
at least in its broad strokes, the way astrology is done by practitioners even to this very day.
That it's a question of charting the movements of the Sun and Moon and planets,
V's of V, the 12 constellations that make up the zodiac disk.
and then a scribing particular meaning
to various confluences and events.
And so something very like the modern version
is already in place by the time we're in like
the six-century BC.
All right, well, with that framework laid out,
we're gonna go ahead and take our first break
And we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part
of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Poised between East and West,
between Orthodox and Catholic,
Lithuania, the last of your-
Europe's pagan nations did not forget its ancient tales such as that of the giant
Tess Naringa, Eglay Queen of Serpents, and the Iron Wolf.
Rather, they fulfilled and enriched them with legends like the Hill of Crosses and the
miracle-working icon of our Lady of the Gate of the Dawn.
In the Wolf and the Cross, Father Andrew Stephen Damek and Deacon Seraphim Richard
Rollin, take a very personal pilgrimage into a land where history and
legend have met and fused, where Orthodox Christians have lived as a minority for nearly seven
centuries.
Their faith founded upon the blood of martyrs and the witness of dozens of saints.
To find this book and others like it, you can go to store.AncientFaith.com.
Again, that is store.AncientFaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits.
the father Andrew Stephen Damick and father Stephen to young.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, welcome back, everybody.
You're probably going to believe this father Stephen,
but we have pretty much a full call board now suddenly.
People are interested in this topic. It turns out...
Clearly it's the dawning of the age of Aquarius.
So our first caller is Trevor who is in Oregon, which is one of the five states that I have not yet visited.
It's not on purpose. I'm not avoiding Oregon, just like I'm not avoiding Arkansas. I just haven't gotten there yet.
So please accept my apologies, Trevor.
Can you hear me?
Yes.
God bless you.
Welcome.
Lord of Spheres podcast.
Thank you very much.
I had a quick question.
The fifth ecumenical council seems to prohibit teaching that the Sun, Moon and Stars are rational beings.
I was wondering if that had an influence on orthodox theology, on astrology.
So what is that all about, Father Stephen?
What exactly does it say there at the Fifth Ecumenical Council regarding the Sun and the Moon and the Stars being?
What do you say, rational beings?
Yeah, well, you are tracking with us.
So we are going to get to what happens with Christianity and astrology later on.
Yeah, so what they are trying to do, right, is they are trying to differentiate between
experience that may be associated with a thing and the thing itself, as it were.
Yeah, the actual anathema says, if anyone shall say that the sun, the moon, and the stars
are also reasonable beings, and that they have only become what they are because they
turn towards evil, let him be anathema.
That's what it says.
which follows on in a...
big long an asthma about, yeah referencing various levels of angels and all this kind of stuff.
Right. So this is, yeah. So that's, that is specifically a gnostic thing. Right. So you have to,
But you have to remember, the Gnostic idea is that things have...
or being spirits have fallen to varying degrees.
And the degree to which they have fallen, right?
Cause they're really, oh, there's really a sort of monad,
monadic view, everything is really originally
and ultimately one.
But the degree to which things have fallen
is the degree to which they participate in materiality.
Yeah, I mean, you know, if you read,
So these are the unathomers again.
origin, I'm looking at them right now, if you read the one that's immediately before this,
which this one seems to be referencing, like there's the logical connection between them,
it starts out by saying, if anyone shall say that the creation of all reasonable beings
includes only intelligences without bodies and altogether immaterial, having neither number nor name,
etc., etc., etc., in other words, like if the creation is ultimately just sort of spiritual,
if that's the claim, then that's, that's.
anathema because later on that line actually goes on to say that no, they have bodies.
You know, there's this connection with actual bodies.
Right.
So the idea would be that there were all these spirits, they fell to varying degrees.
Humans fell farther than like the Sun, Moon, and stars.
Yeah.
Right.
celestial beings.
And then humans fell farther because we're more material, we're more earthen than material.
And then like the earth itself, you know, in Adam, what we would call inanimate objects
fell the farthest, right?
Something's fell to being irrational animals.
That's what's being condemned there.
So there's a differentiation being made.
The problem is not saying God has angelic beings that govern.
the movements of the cosmos, or there are angelic beings and saints who are patrons of places and things on earth.
The problem is making this number one direct identification between the two.
Right. And then secondly, this idea that it's fallen into materiality.
So the moon is itself, there would be a say the moon is itself an angel.
It's a fallen angel, and you know, it's a fallen angel because it's become material.
Yeah. Yeah. I mean, the whole this whole series of anathema is about origin is
them, you know, and all of the kind of problems related to that. So, yeah,
there's no elements of that would affect Mormonism, frankly. Yeah, absolutely.
Absolutely.
So, all right.
Hopefully that answers your question, Trevor.
Yes, thank you. Great. All right. We're going to move on now to we've got another question from someone in a state where you probably can see the stars pretty well as long as you're not in Phoenix and that's Zach in Arizona. Zach.
Welcome to the lower spurious podcast.
I am in Phoenix.
No stars.
I can see not a single star in the sky right now.
I am in Phoenix.
Oh no stars.
I can see not a single star in the sky right now.
Phoenix proper or like Mesa or 10p. Yeah, yeah proper. Okay. Well, I mean, that's a city that could not exist without air conditioning. Just putting that out there.
That's what I do for a living.
That job security right there.
I went, you know, we had we had our archdiocese convention in Phoenix a couple of years ago in July.
And I remember going outside and I could feel this breeze coming and I thought oh it's nice it's a breeze nope nope
It's 118 degrees. It's an oven. It's opening an oven. That's what it is.
Yeah, there ought to be a there ought to be a law, Zach. I don't know, you know, you guys.
It's a dry heat.
An oven is a dry heat, Father Steven. I've spent a lot of time in Phoenix at different times.
So all right. So what is your what's your question, Zach, before we reg on your weather anymore?
My question was about, it kind of kind of follows up at that last question nicely.
but it was about the book of Enoch. And in the book of Enoch, there's obviously a lot made of
astrology and the stars and the patterns. But one of the things I was curious about is when Enoch
talks about the, he's always talking about the seven planets and the sun and the moon and he
calls them wandering stars and then Saint Jude refers back to that. What do you think the validity
is with that. Like why that those particular ones are out of balance. Is there any validity to
that and like what's going on there I guess is my question. That is definitely a question
for you father. Yeah so yeah well the wandering stars has to do with the planets thing that
their motion didn't describe right to the other ones and Enic is also referencing the fact
that as we've mentioned for centuries by that time those celestial bodies have been associated
with particular...
social advisor associated with particular pagan gods,
who of course they considered to be fallen spirits, right? And so
and this in some detail, right, there's a there's a journal article
that title's not going to come to me. It's talking about whether he'll bench a car in Isaiah
that gets translated as Lucifer Star.
the morning by St. Jerome about it talking about N-Lil, but it gets into the astrology of it.
So there's astrology in there too. The reason that the sort of inverted star, like the pentagram
shape comes to be associated with the devil is that that is roughly the path.
If you assume the earth is stationary and you math the path of Venus in the sky, it roughly
traces a star shape like that.
It looks more like the Elder sign in Lovecraft.
It's not like a perfect star.
It's like wobbly to the side.
But basically, right, that's how that symbol cozy can associate with it.
And so I think that's what that is aimed at, both inextra-
reference and Saint Jude's reference back to it is sort of doubling down on what the
pagans are. The pagans are associating these with their gods and it's like, yeah, look,
they're wandering. They're disordered. They're not following Phenomos, right? The other
stars follow. And that's sort of being symbolic of them being demons of the corset. Jude
is comparing false teachers to fallen angels.
right who are out to make a following for themselves and pull people away from
God the same way that those fallen spirits did in the form of the pagan
gods. Is that help Zach? Yeah that's that's definitely helpful because it's
I was just always wondering because there is there's obviously something with the
that there's be seven in every major culture.
makes a big deal out of it and then Enoch comes out from a different perspective. So I just
was trying to try and understand that a little more but that's yeah that's helpful.
All right thank you very much for calling. We're going to talk now to Monica from Connecticut. So
Monica welcome to the Lotus Peers podcast.
Hi, can you hear me? We can hear you. We're in Connecticut. Are you if I may ask?
Kalek is not that bad.
It's not that bad, yes.
I'm in welfare.
you're in Milford. All right. Well, I mean, my dad is from South
England. Oh, really? Yeah, yeah, I've been in your neighborhood many, many times.
Yep. My grandpa is buried in New Haven. Well, near New Haven. But yeah, yeah. So,
all right. Well, we've got an actual Yankee calling. So, welcome. What's on your
mine Monica from Connecticut. So I had always thought of.
astrology, like it always seems like a little BS silly to me, but I know people who are really into it. And I always thought like the credence that I, I would give it is like, okay, well, if you're born in like the dead of winter.
And your first year on Earth is the experience of like everybody miserable and cold.
And then the world getting better and then it becoming miserable and cold again.
That's like...
a really different experience from somebody who's like born in the middle of summer and
everything is wonderful and then it gets miserable and cold and then it gets one. You know what I
mean? And so I feel like that that like isn't this all just kind of like correlation is not causation
when we're talking about like where the stars are and like what like it makes sense of like
like a clock and they're, you know,
we're talking broader astrology too, like a-
it does make sense like that humanity we move we have seasons you know even if we don't notice it
all the time and the stars are in their patterns because every that's that's the pattern I don't
know and maybe I'm not articulating this very well but that's just like my sense of it and I was
wondering if you could comment on it. I think I have a sense of what you what you mean um I mean I
I don't honestly I don't
know if there's anything that could be shown about how humans, I don't know, human personality
based on their initial experience of the weather. I don't know. I mean, if you're a tiny baby,
you're probably not dealing with the dead of winter very much if your mother and father
are doing their job.
And I mean, we're gonna actually get to this a little bit of
special.
the third half of this episode, this question about, you know, when what time of year you were
born and so forth, what effect that has on you. But like, I, for instance, share a birthday
with Rebecca DeMorne, Elliott Gold, and Michael Jackson and John McCain. But I don't think that we
have a lot in common, the several of us personality wise. Oh, also, Archbishop Michael of New York and
New Jersey. We have the same birthday as well. But other than you and Michael Jackson, I see no
connections. What's up?
locked. Hey, you need thriller. But so yeah, I mean, okay, yes, the idea that the movement
of the stars and the planets and so forth provide this kind of conceptual framework for
the ancient world. Absolutely. Absolutely. That's definitely a lot of what's going on.
that is some
kind of predictive divinizing, not divinizing, divination, technique, or something like this,
or as we just heard, this idea that it has to do with specific gods and their attitude towards
you and so forth. Yeah, that's not identical to just simply having the movements of the heavens
be part of your framework for understanding the world and how it all works together and what
what it means.
you know, now you can put those things together obviously,
many cultures have, but you don't have to.
But we're going to get more into that as we go.
So does that make sense? Monica?
Yeah, thank you.
Very good.
Okay, we're going to take one more call before we move on.
That whole morning, the dead of winter thing might go a long way
to explaining why the Dutch are the way we are.
That's true.
Your winter is on the lengthy side compared to a lot of the
world. Yeah, we have we have an angry
caller from from Montana, probably
sick of all of our Montana and Wyoming
related jokes. So Luke, are you are you
here to to tell off, Father Steven?
The few. Yeah, I'm here. All right, tell
them off. Tell them what you think of
all of his his depopulation jokes.
Oh, you can't really get the joke
much. That's okay. It's okay. What is on
your mind.
Luke from Montana. So I had a question about, you know,
because in the Bible and Christian tradition, the angels are the start,
there's a strong connection between the angels and the stars. So if that's the
case, like, why isn't there a, why aren't there particular connections between
angels and stars? As you know, I mean, like, why aren't the seven archangels
associated with the seven cross-all plants.
Yeah, I mean, isn't that kind of what CS Lewis does in the space trilogy?
As I recall, he has these makes these connections.
Something like that.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
It's been a little bit since I read it.
But so, yeah, what's the deal?
Is this another, you know, way into the third half kind of thing?
Partially.
The identification of the seven archagels with the directly with the seven plants.
Number 7 is...
bear significance, there is a connection with the number itself. But in terms of this one is Michael
this one's Gabriel this one's Gereal, etc. Right. It's just one that doesn't really happen in
in Jewish
theology at any point. The reason I slow down is I'm just sort of double checking in my brain trying
the thing if I can do anything like that.
Yeah, and I think the reason it doesn't happen is that so the term archangel is used in two
different ways.
There is a rank of angels called archangels, right?
It's the second lowest rank.
There's angels, archangels, and then you work your way up.
There are thousands of angels in that rank of archangels.
Okay. The seven archangels is archangel being used differently. It's being used more like the way we talk about someone being made in arch praise or in archdeacon.
We're saying these are the seven top angels.
But the seven top angels are not from the order of archangels.
So for example, if you read the text for the...
peace of Saint Michael, they identify him as a seraphim.
Yeah.
Right. And even though traditionally the devil was one of the archangels,
was one of the seven archangels, um, we're told it is a heal that he was a
cherub. He was a cherub. Um, so yeah. So archangel gets used differently.
And so I think I think that's why, um,
whereas there's a class of angels. When you find Jewish and early Christian writers writing about
the angelic beings who are associated with the stars, they usually associate them with the powers.
The powers of heaven. That's the rank to which they ascribe them. And the seven archangels
are generally not considered to be of that rank.
Yeah, the ranks, remember, are not ranks like you get promoted.
Like, you know, getting moved off of fries to patties at McDonald's.
It's getting your wings.
Yeah, no, it's, it's their job description, the job they're assigned to.
And so the idea is that the seven archangels governing planets
not the job they're assigned to.
Yeah, yeah. So you though there is a connection with the number seven. It's not that direct to like each one of those associated with one of the seven arching.
Yeah, there's not a one to one correlation.
I hope that helps Luke from Montana.
Yeah, I think so.
All right, very good. Thank you very much for calling.
All right. Well, here in the second half are each of the seven residents of Montana.
associated with the seven counties, one of the seven counties that comprise Montana.
I would have liked to have seen Montana.
Yeah, so we kind of in the first half laid out, I shouldn't say kind of, we laid out in
the first half the sort of framework for astrology that's particularly in the engineering
and he did it with a lacquerity.
That's right.
that were, but now...
going to talk about astrology in the Old Testament, astrology and Judaism. So now it's going to get maybe
slightly uncomfortable for some people. But we did already kind of tip our hands with that as
Ezekiel stuff. So it's not like we're making this up. So yeah, what is up with that? I mean
there's there's some obvious numbers that would seem to go with zodiac like there's 12s in various
places. Who we what's up with. Yeah. Yeah. I mean so.
So what is, I mean, is there an is-relight astrology?
Is that a thing?
Yes.
Yeah.
But so how does it, how does it work?
What does the map look like?
Yeah.
So what are the, what are the first places we see this
with certain significant biblical numbers?
OK.
So we talked about the number seven,
right that sun moon
five planets, right? And so those seven come to represent the seven bodies in the heavens, sometimes the seven heavens, right?
It's taken even more literally than that and sort of each one of those bodies presides over a
quote unquote, layer of the heavens, a severe as it were.
That of course presupposes that you.
like everyone for the last 2500 years knows that the earth is a sphere, but wait
what? Yes, I know. Oh, there's always somebody. There'll be somebody in the
YouTube comments. I know. I know. How dare you block flat earthers?
So right, but so that number, the seven of them, seven then becomes a number that
signifies.
sort of totality, the totality of the cosmos, right?
The totality of the universe, the totality of creation, right?
And you find that right away on page one of your Bible
with the seven days of creation, right?
God creates the heavens of the earth in seven days.
So then because of that, you have seven days of the week
in the, we talked about this in the episode
we talked about the tabernacle.
tabernacle you have the lamp stand with seven lights. The reason it has seven lights is that the tabernacle remember is a microcosm of the heavenly tabernacle.
right of the place where God dwells in the heavens that Moses entered into a
top Mount Sinai that is then reconstructed on earth.
itself sort of an icon so that when people enter into it they are entering into the place
where God dwells in the heavens.
So you see the number seven right away continues to carry the sort of astrological significance
in the Bible.
The other number, of course, that gets carried over that has.
as clear astrological significance as 12.
The most obvious form of that,
there are actually a bunch of 12s in the Bible,
even in just the Old Testament or the Hebrew Bible,
but the most prominent one obviously
is the 12 tribes of Israel.
And in, we can say for certain,
for certain that by the time you get to second.
temple Judaism that not only is the number of the tribes, i.e. there are 12 tribes, there are 12
major constellations in the zodiac. Not only are those broadly considered to be connected in terms
of number, like we were just talking about with the seven archangels, but they're taken to be directly
related in.
the sense that by the Second Temple period, the tribes are associated with particular constellations
in the heavens. And the sources, the Second Temple sources are as sources we have. So we're talking
about Second Temple, we're talking about post-exileic.
So beginning roughly 515 BC through the end of the first century AD.
Those sources, when they talk about this, when they ascribe and connect the tribes to the constellations of the Zodiac,
they point to two major passages of the Torah.
One of those is, and we've talked about this at least in brief, we
at least mentioned this before. On the show, one of those is Genesis 49, which is the story of
what we've called the Testament of Jacob where Jacob gathers his 12 sons and speaks sort of prophetic
words to them, not so much about them individually, but about the tribes that will be descended from them
in the future.
And
I
In a number of those, there are particular animals who are associated, the imagery of those animals is used to describe, prophetically, that tribe.
The most famous and obvious one of these, the one that sort of everyone knows about is the connection between Judah and the lion.
Yeah.
Yeah, right. That's just the most I everyone knows that one
The other passage is one that's a little S well known and I don't know that we've talked about
On this show at least before and that is numbers chapter two
Everybody's probably most favorite book
You've waited through that census data
there. And now you get
to the cool part, which is the way the tribes were laid out their tents when they made camp
in the wilderness.
Yeah.
So I can tell everyone is excited.
Yeah, there's a lot of excitement over the chat over these census data and the relative
real estate.
Yes, in the camp, right?
But if you read numbers too...
You'll see that the way it is laid out is actually the way the Babylonian zodiac was laid out.
Meaning there are four cardinal tribes.
describes four tribes, Judah, Ruben, Ephraim.
And Dan, right, who are Dan is North, Ruben is East, Ephraim is West, Judah is South.
Nor they also know that corresponds to where they're going to settle in the land too.
Yes, it's the north being done done done done.
Yeah, then.
And so.
But you may also be recognizing some things like Judah being one of those of being associated with the lion.
Ruben we're going to find out is associated with a boulder and an ox.
And then there are two tribes on either side of each of those cardinal tribes.
That's the way numbers describes it and lays it out.
So it's laid out in numbers the way Enzoniac was typically laid out in the ancient world.
And so again at least by the time of the second temple period,
We have readers of the text, those who are studying the Torah, have noticed this and have made these assignments.
And I'm going to run through which tribe is which symbol relatively quickly.
You'll have a recording. You can pause. You can roll back and stuff.
Now, let me say, the ones I'm going to give are sort of the majority version.
Yeah, there's a very good in this point.
Yeah, like what you may remember when we talked about the seven archangels on the show,
when you find lists of the seven archangels in both church fathers and
Jewish writings before that.
You always find St. Michael, you always find St. Gabriel, you always find St. Rafael,
you always find St.
Uriel.
Then the other three things happen, right?
I mean
even uriel though sometimes you get yeah yeah so then you get a lot more variation right um
beyond those and the same is really true here with the 12 tribes like june is always a lion right
there's certain of these that are just always right um but uh the uh there are some of them where you'll
you'll find them, if you find a particular list
in a particular text, a couple of them will be switched,
will be swapped.
And those are like some of the lesser known tribes,
like GAD and Asher.
Right, like those are the ones that you'll find flipped.
But the major tribes like Judah, Ephraim, Rubin,
Dan, those are pretty much constant.
Right. But so the ones have a
the most common ones. So Judah is associated with the lion, as we mentioned
now several times, Issaqar with a maiden, Zebulin with a fish, Ruben with a
boulder and ox, Simian with a goat, Gad with a ram, Ephraim with water, or some
kind of water feature like a waterfall or water jar.
with menacea with scales,
Benjamin with a,
well, it's the constellation that later the Greeks
are gonna call a crab,
but before that of the extravieries,
it wasn't dragon, which is way cooler than a crab.
Much.
Dan with a serpent,
Asher with an archer
and, uh, naphthily with twins.
So those are the general, like I said, some of those are constants.
Yeah.
In the major tribes, some of those you'll find flipped.
And some of those, I mean, if you know the traditional names of the constellations from
the Greco Latin tradition, some of those obviously can be familiar to you.
Match up pretty well, right?
Yeah.
like the dragon crab thing.
So that's right you go.
that a fiddle with them a little bit.
Nice.
Yes.
So the reason I keep saying at least by the second
table period is just we don't have any text before that.
So if someone wants to say we're going to talk about this
more in a little bit, but if someone wants to say,
oh, well, that's something that comes in after the
exile in Babylon.
They start doing astrology stuff.
They didn't do it before.
that. We don't have a lot of evidence to prove that one way or the other, right? But we
know at least by that. By the time we get to Josephus for sure and we have other sources
that talk about this too, but Josephus records. Other reason Josephus is important in this
regard is that Josephus was alive when there was a high priest actually doing high priestly
things at the temple in Jerusalem. He says that the
bones on the high priest's ephid that represented the 12 tribes had the constellations related
to that tribe etched into them.
Yeah, which, you know, that's not mentioned in the Bible, but he might well have seen it
himself or, you know, he was certainly have been around.
It would have been weird for him to say that if that's not how it was at least in his time.
in his time, right?
Yeah.
hypothetically those could have been the original stones, but probably not. Right, they're
probably had to reconstruct that during the, when they were reconstructing the temple.
Yeah, I'm just telling you about the mix of.
But I mean, it's possible, but I mean, it'd be hard to argue that those were the original
stones. And therefore, this goes all the way back to Moses, right? But when, how long
exactly that was true.
We can't prove.
But at least then, that was the case.
Obviously, the calendar, there's two of the calendar,
calendar texts.
One of the colors brought up the book of Enoch,
a big chunk of witches, right?
The laying out the Anachic calendar, all
of the calendar debates that we're going on in the second
temple period about whether to follow the Ferrisay at calendar
the pagan, Julian calendar that the Sadducees started using once it came into being
in the first century BC. The inocent calendar and probably others that we don't
know about anymore, other variations, were all those arguments that were related to
the motions of heavenly bodies, directly related to...
astrological observations. And assuming that those astrological observations, the reason
why we're still calling this astrology is assuming that those were purposeful. That God had
arranged things in the heaven to work, heavens to work the way that they did and that that
should be reflected in human life, because that was represented God's divine order.
Right. So there is this level of meaning being ascribed, which makes it still a kind of astrology.
And then one of the most telling things is that we have now archaeologically found a number,
kind of a surprising number of first century AD synagogues in Galilee.
Now part of the reason for that is that the Romans came through at the end of the first century and demolished them
and buried them
right
That's why there's still there and archaeologists can dig them up now
Right right deliberately right demolished them and buried them
But so
these include
Citigogs in cities where the Gospels tell us
cities of Galilee where the Gospels tell us
us, Christ went to those cities and preached in the synagogue.
So it's possible that when he would have probably even, that when he would have walked
into the synagogue, he would have seen what we're talking about here.
Yeah.
And what we're talking about here are mosaics in the entryway laying out the zodiac with
Hebrew inscriptions.
So
And we have no commentary from Christ on this fact recorded anywhere, positive or negative.
Right?
Yeah.
But this seems to have just been the case.
That's in August and Galilee, where Christ was and where the apostles were living as Jewish
people.
So we know that
astrology was going on in Jewish circles throughout the Second Temple period. And in particular,
in the first century AD, that certain kinds of astrology and elements of astrology were
at that point, part and parcel of Jewish religious discussions.
debates. Now you will get all kinds of arguments, especially the scholarly literature, because journal
articles must be published, dissertations must be written, about which came first. Yeah, this. Yeah.
Did Israelites derive these things from a...
pagan zodiac, or is the zodiac stuff being kind of attached in later to all this existing
theory?
You know, is the whole 12 tribes of Israel thing nonsense?
This is just an astrological thing, and they're writing essentially astrological myths,
on sort of the more liberal side.
Or...
on the more conservative Protestant scholarship side
is astrology just totally evil
and this can't possibly have been acceptable.
And therefore,
this is all just a few sort of paganized Jews here and there.
Making this stuff up or ascribing pagan symbolism to things
And had nothing to do with astrology.
whatever originally, right? And you know, people like to argue. But the problem with, with trying
to make either of those cases is that they're both examples of motivated reasoning, meaning in both
cases, you start with your conclusion and argue backwards from it. So if you've already decided that
astrology.
is evil and pagan, then definitionally the faithful Jews at least cannot have been involved
with it in any way. Therefore all of this stuff must be weird accretions of the second
temple period by faithless Jewish people. Or if you start with the conclusion that Judy
Thank you.
just another form, the real Judaism that actually ingested
was just another form of ancient Near Eastern paganism.
Right, that's been whitewashed, right?
By later generations and rewritten
then this astrology stuff you're gonna argue is,
oh, this is the real pagan Judaism
like creeping out around the edges, right?
This is the rare truth,
but in both of those cases
You've just asserted your...
inclusion. Yeah, and I mean, it's and they're both based on this this bifurcation of the world
into these two radically different worldviews, you know, that either that must have existed or
that that do exist, you know, that the Christianity and Judaism are this one view of the spiritual
world and then paganism is completely different view of the spiritual world.
And so, you know, it's either one or the other and that's just the way that it is.
But the problem is when you start actually looking really closely as we're doing.
At the scriptures.
What you get is actually they all kind of have a very similar world view in terms of their understanding of.
How the world works.
The question is really.
What do you do about that?
What is the.
They're looking at the same landscape from different perspective.
perspectives. Yeah, they don't disagree about the landscape. Right. Right. They don't disagree that the spirits exist. They disagree about whether they have your best intentions in mind. Yeah. Right. That's right.
So that's the key difference.
And so we don't need to do any of this motivated reasoning.
We could just take what the scriptures say at face value.
And astrological stuff.
Fairly detailed astrological stuff is in the Bible.
Okay. The exhibit A of this is probably Psalm 19 in the Hebrew numbering, 18 in the Greek
numbering verses 1 through 6. Yeah, which says this,
the heavens declare the glory of God and the firmament proclaims his handiwork. Day to day pours
out speech and night to night reveals knowledge. There is no speech nor are there
words whose voice is not heard. Their line goes out through all the earth and their words
to the end of the world. In them he has set a tent for the sun which comes out like a
bridegroom leaving his chamber, and like a strong man runs its course with joy. Its rising
is from the end of the heavens, and its circuit to the end of them, and there is nothing hidden
from its heat. Yeah, so that line that it talks about going out through all the earth is what's
It's called the Ecliptic in a Sralid.
which is sort of the medium line, and it happens against which you judge the relationship of various heavenly bodies, and then it describes the sun sort of circumnavigating the ecliptic.
So that's astrology.
It's attributing the creation of all of these things in the heavens to God.
But it's also saying they pour
for speech, the cluttering God's glory, meaning they're
communicating. Right. And that communication element is the key
element. This is what separates Jewish astrology from pagan
astrology. Right. Again, not the fact that there's a zodiac, not
the fact that there's an ecliptic, not the fact even that they
associate spirits with these different heavenly bodies. Right.
But this element of speech. And so we're going to read it's fairly lengthy and you've heard it before on this show if you've listened to every episode.
But it's been a minute and it's important. So what's again, Philo of Alexandria, the first century BC.
It's going to tell us the difference between Jewish astrology and pagan astrology. And it's not that it was rejected. Yeah, it's like it.
And, and Philo is a Jew living in Alexandria, okay?
So this is what he says. It is a little bit lengthy, so just listen closely.
Some persons have conceived that the sun and the moon and the other stars are independent
gods, to whom they have attributed the causes of all things that exist. But Moses was well
aware that the world was created and was like a very large city having rulers and subjects
in it. The rulers being all the bodies which are in heaven, such as planets and fixed
stars and the subjects being all the natures beneath.
the moon, hovering in the air and adjacent to the earth, but that the rulers of force
that are not independent and absolute, but are the voice-roys of the one supreme being
the father of all, in imitation of whom they administer with propriety and success, the
charge committed to their care as he also presides over all created things in strict accordance
with justice and with law. Others on the contrary, who have not discovered the supreme governor,
with us rules everything.
I've attributed the causes of the
different things which exist in the world to the subordinate powers, as if they had brought
them to pass by their own independent act. But the most sacred law giver changes their
ignorance into knowledge, speaking in the following manner, thou shalt not, when thou
seeest the sun and the moon and the stars and all the host of heaven be let astray and
fall down and worship them. By the way, that is a reference to Deuteronomy. He goes on,
with great felicity and propriety has he here called the reception of these bodies as gods
an error for they who see that
different seasons of the year owe their existence to the advances and retreats of the sun, in which periods
also the generation of animals and plants and fruits are perfected according to well-defined times,
and who see also that the moon is the servant and successor of the sun, taking that care and
superintendents of the world by night, which the sun takes by day, and also that the other stars
in accordance with their sympathy with things on earth, labor continually and do 10,000 things,
which contribute to the duration of the existing-
state of things have been led into an inextricable error, imagining that these bodies are the only
gods. We're skipping ahead a little bit here. We must therefore look on all those bodies in the
heaven, which the outward sense regards as gods, not as independent rulers, since they are assigned
the work of lieutenants, being by their intrinsic nature responsible to a higher power. But by
reason to their virtue not actually called to render in an account of their
doings, so that transcending all visible essence by means of our reason, let us press forward
to that to the honor of that everlasting and invisible being who can be comprehended and appreciated
by the mind alone, who's not only the God of all gods, whether appreciable only by the
intellect or visible to the outward senses, but is also the Creator of them all.
And if anyone gives up the service due to the everlasting and uncreated God transferring
it to any more modern and created beam.
letting me sit down as mad and as liable to the charge of the greatest impiety.
So he goes on a bit, but the key takeaways here you should get is, look, these other,
these heavenly beings are indeed in charge of the world, but under God and they are created.
They didn't create, they didn't make things, they didn't make things come into being.
God does that.
they serve God. In fact, that's the way it's known how many times he uses the word independent.
They're not independent as his biggest point. They're lesser beings that God is in charge of.
God of God's. Right. And they communicate like good angels, right? Messengers, they bring
messengers to God. God can use them to communicate things like say the birth of the Messiah.
to tease our third half about that.
Right. Like God can use them to communicate certain things, but they themselves, as
well as any center, are not sort of independent actors who should be independently worshipped
and appeased and lobbied to do particular things with gifts of animal blood, etc.
Yeah, don't do that. Don't worship them.
So
Yeah, the gods exist.
Don't worship them.
Worship God only.
This is the action to take here.
So, all right, well with that said,
we're gonna go ahead and take our second and final break
and we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Ancient near-Eastern texts, such as the Ball Cycle, portray the pagan god Ball as a
revel, the hero of a revolution, worshiped and glorified for his long string of victories.
In the Ball Book, a biography of the devil, Father Stephen D. Young shows that the Hebrew
scriptures consciously turn the ball story on its head, depicting him as a failed and defeated
who nonetheless tries to steal the glory that belongs to Almighty God.
From these scriptures, the figure of the devil emerged within Jewish and Christian tradition.
Father DeYoung works through the old and new testament passages that refer to various ball stories,
and he surveys ball worship through followers' beliefs, religious practices, and liturgical life.
life. In these pages, we will see that the figures of Ball and the devil, the prince,
of demons are one and the same. To find this book and others like it, you can go to store.enchantfaith.com
Again, that is store.enchantfaith.com. We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the
father Andrew Stephen Damick and father Stephen DeYoung. If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
237 2346. That's 855 AF radio.
You got to love the ominous music in that add-out.
It's not as cool as the actual animated commercial though.
That was pretty metal.
You guys need to put that up as like a YouTube short or something.
Yeah.
People.
But before we go on, so I of course have my phone muted while we're broadcasting the show live and everything.
but there are ways to contact me.
Should it...
emergency rise. And I've received important breaking news. Oh, and I have to inform our listeners of
it was just announced at the game awards that they're releasing a decades away
in sequel tonight's of the Old Republic. Yes, my son texted this to me called faint of the
the old Republic. That's right. He texted us to be about 25 minutes ago. He's the same
game director as the...
the original. And the buyer
and the old. Well, I mean, the
sequel to see this is the
important news that they come
to us to hear when they
listen to this show. The
original was was magnificent.
The sequel was less than that.
The sequel is somewhat
underrated. The sort of
restored addition that you
could get as a mod, which
you know, digs all the stuff
out of the data and kind of
fixes the story, whatever.
makes it much better, makes it much better.
Yeah.
And Ed Asner's voice acting is amazing.
In the second one.
Yeah, I thought that the original should have been made into a film.
I don't know why.
The original was like an all-time classic.
The other things that still holds up today.
Absolutely.
Story wise.
So you're welcome audience.
So we pass this along to you.
Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. So, okay. So, I mean, if we have any more colors, we don't not not at the moment.
So, you know, I guess people are just so stunned by that news. They don't know what to do with
themselves. They're going out there and seeing they can pre-order. They're all going to watch
the trailer on YouTube right now. Yeah. Yeah. Actually, I got someone to go away and pause us and
go watch the McCribbs song.
by Zanthi, I can't remember her last name now,
which is now 10 years old.
Did you know that the McCrib song is now 10 years old?
Why would you do that to yourself during a fast?
How would you tantalize yourself in such a way?
Someone in the chat was asking about this
and I was like, they said something like
that I didn't get to have a McCrib before the fast started
and I was like, but I did watch the McCrib song
a couple of times so that's not bad.
It's not bad.
I guess you could get one of those like vegan rib patty things.
Let's knock harvest burger bags at a roll and like can you do harvest spicy with a vegan
Macrub patty?
I don't you can't do you can't be can't do excess of sea.
No, you're not supposed to either way because whatever that was made out of had no organs.
That's right.
I mean, I guess a statement is technically an organ.
Okay, so you know, we laid out kind of the ancient Near Eastern and general framework of
the world in terms of astrology in the first half.
And the second half we showed how that really actually is represented, particularly in the
old testament.
So why yeah, Jewish folks seem like they were kind of cool with it as long as, you know,
why is it done for the certain perspective?
does not seem to be a Christian.
astrology is there like what's what's going? No, there's not. And in fact, there's this very
important figure in this regard. He's actually an important figure in a couple of regards, but this
is one of them named Aquila of Cinope. Okay. Not to be there. There were a lot of people named Aquila.
Yeah, as I say, not to be considered a couple of the Bible. As an Aquila and Priscilla, that's not
not the same. It's just, it's a room.
name. Yeah. So Aquila of
Sinape who we're talking about the
early part of the second century AD.
He was a Roman, he worked for
Hadrian. The Roman Emperor Hadrian, who
you may remember from our last
episode. Yeah, the wall guy. Yes,
Well, that's not what we talked about in the last-
No, no, it's not, but I've been trying to block that out of my mind. So okay.
But he was a radio. So the thing he's probably more famous for than what we're about to talk about, than his biographical details is that he is one of three people, along with Samakis and Theodosian, who after the early rise of Christianity,
Christianity.
attempted to re-translate the Greek translation of the Hebrew Bible to make it less prone
to Christian readings.
To go back to the Hebrew, do a new Greek translation because the old Greek translation Christians
had latched onto.
And we're using some of the particulars of that translation to argue for particular points
of Christianity.
Christian doctrine over and over against those Jewish folks who did not accept Jesus as the Messiah.
And this gets mentioned by St. Justin Martyr in his dialogue with TRIFO.
Please listen closely.
Yes. So all of you hearing this?
Yes. Right. And so some people having come across this passage from St. Justin Martyr,
where he says you have altered the scriptures.
So that they don't basically so they'll give Christian reading.
You have all of the examples at one point.
Yeah, yeah.
The old readings and new readings.
There are people who read that and say, ah, ah, ah, ah.
This is Saint Justin Martyr telling everybody that the maseritic text, the Hebrew maseritic
text of the Old Testament has become the maseritic text.
Yes.
Has been altered.
That's not what he's referring to. He's referring to...
to somebody munking with a Greek translation, making a new Greek translation.
We're redoing the Greek translation. That is what he is talking about.
Yeah.
Talking about that. Get a rid of the old Greek translations from the synagogues.
And either going back to the Hebrew original or using one of these new Greek translations.
Yeah, because I don't think could just could say Justin read Hebrew like what he.
and probably at least new airmac.
Okay, because he's from Nablus. Okay. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
So he's probably at least fluent in Aramaic.
So that's pretty close.
Yeah, so
But that's what he's talking about.
Okay, he is not talking about the Master of Text we've
advocated. We know for certain from the Dead Sea Scrolls that the
text that became the Master of Edict text existed at least in the
3rd century BC.
in Hebrew. Virtually, identically, to what it looks like today. Okay. So leave off with that nonsense.
Right. When you make that argument, it just makes you look weird because it's not historically true.
Yeah. And people who have studied this know it's not historically true. Yeah, just non-Christian Jewish
groups did try
to change the Greek translation and ultimately abandon the Greek translations of the Hebrew Bible
of the Old Testament because of Christianity. That is true, right? That is absolutely true. But
say, Justin is talking about them altering the Greek translations. An Aquila of Cinepe is one of
the people who did that. Now, Aquila is not a Jewish name. No, it's a Roman name again.
Right.
And in fact, if you see a referred to in Jewish sources,
he's referred to as Aquila the Prasalite,
which is essentially Aquila the Convert.
Yeah.
So how did this happen?
Well, not only did he work for Hadrian,
but he's one of the top guys who Hadrian sent,
not his favorites, that's something else
as we found out last episode.
But one of the top guys who he
to reconstruct Jerusalem. So, Hadrian turned Jerusalem into Alia Capitolina, rebuilt the city,
following the Roman destruction of 70, and just his own urban renewal efforts, and that's part
of what triggered the barcocferable.
So Aquila is one of the people who was sent there to supervise reconstruction projects.
The re-constructed Jerusalem, by the way, had a big pillar with a giant statue of Hadrian
on top of it, overlooking the city.
So Acquila was sent there and Acquila ended up becoming a Christian.
He became a Christian, he went back to Rome as a Christian, and then the Bishop of Rome
at the time excommunicated him for practicing astrology.
And so when he was excommunicated from the Christian community in Rome for practicing astrology,
converted to Judaism.
I became a quote, the process light went back to Palestine
and became a disciple of Rabbi Akiva.
So yes, so we're talking about around 130 AD,
AD 130.
Yeah, so why I was communicating with this.
His whip...
here right because we were just talking about Josephus in the first century and it like totally
cool with this astrology astrology stuff in Judaism. And now within like one or two generations
Christianity is like no you cannot practice astrology at all period right.
Quick turnaround right. And
And the reasons for it are not sort of at first obvious.
Because, for example, in the New Testament, in Romans 10, St. Paul quotes Psalm 19, 18 in the Greek,
that we talked about in the last half, and talks about the gospel being proclaimed to the Gentiles
by the stars of the heavenly bodies.
That's astrology stuff.
stuff. So yeah, it's a astrology stuff. It's Jewish astrology stuff, right?
that God communicates through these lesser spiritual beings, these angels, he uses them as
messengers to communicate things about himself, to people on earth. So that's typical Jewish stuff
of the first century AD. And there's still in the earliest examples we have, and even in some
cases to this very day.
are astrological symbols used in Christian iconography?
Oh, yeah, totally. I mean, the promotional image for this episode,
if you're looking at it on YouTube right now and a bunch of you are,
is an icon of Christ that's in the dome of a monastery in Greece.
And there he is enthroned. And of course, right next to him,
you see the four living creatures, which as we know,
are four different
installation images, but then the outer ring of that dome, if you look in the outer ring of that, you see
Astrological images there, you know, those are the various
constellations of the zodiac in that outer ring and
I mean, this is not the only place in the Orthodox world where you see the zodiac
Connected with Christ in this particular way
This is just one place. This is a monastery in Greece. I mean this is in some you know weird piece of icon
from, you know, Montana or whatever, this is, this is increased. Right. And unlike non-Christian
Judaism, Christianity continues for centuries, as we've talked about before on the show, to use
texts like Firsteanek and other Second Temple Jewish texts that contain all this astrological
stuff. Right so
Again, at that level, so was it just this one bishop of Rome just really hated astrology?
Like what's going on, right?
Why would this flip?
And I think the key element here, and we're going to go into this more, but the key element
here is that Aquila of Cinepe was condemned not for knowing about astrology or using astrological
symbolism or terminology or...
teaching that God communicates things to people through the movement of heavenly bodies,
he was condemned for practicing astrology.
Hmm.
Right.
And so the key here seems to be, and we'll develop this out, but the key thing here seems
to be the idea that he was practicing astrology in the sense of using astrology as a mode
of divination to tell the future.
to predict the future. Not merely using symbolism or talking about the fact that, you know,
stars led the match eye to Christ's birth, right? This is a different thing. And so we have
relatively early, I mean besides just this one case of acrylics.
in a way, relatively early in the books against heresies and works against the pagans, against
the Greeks, as they were called by most early Christians.
Most early Christians just called pagans Greeks.
Yeah.
Sorry, Greek Orthodox listeners.
But we find in there sort of general condemnations of practicing astrology, but nothing in detail,
I think
It sort of explains here's why we as Christians have rejected this right over against what
apparently was still at least being tolerated within Judaism right.
And so the first place where first two fathers who give us a little detail on this are St.
Augustine and St. John Chrysostom.
Okay.
So, St. Augustine on astrology, this is going to trouble some of you folks because it's
going to kind of demonstrate that you've been reading St. Augustine completely and correctly.
But we'll get there.
So St. Augustine talks about astrology in two different places and in two different contexts
in those two different places.
So one of those is in Confessions 8.
And in Confessions 8, his confessions are basically
his autobiography.
And so there he's talking about the fact
that before he was a Christian,
when he was in the pagan world,
he had an interest in astrology
and gone and dabbled around with it a little bit.
That was interesting as a pagan.
and then ultimately rejected it. The other place he talks about it is in City of God 5.
And in City of God, City of God is more of a theological treatise. And so we get sort of
most of his arguments. There's a few arguments in the confessions, but City of God gives us most
of his sort of overall, you could call it, refute.
right, astrology debunked, right? If it was a YouTube video. So, and the core, there's a spoiler,
the core of St. Augustine's critique of astrology is going to be that astrology requires fatalism.
Wait, I thought Cinda Gustin was into fatalism.
Turns out no!
Right. Sorry Calvinists for the night.
And to be more specific, because our Calvinist friends will say they're not fatalists.
Okay.
Say to Guston, says that astrology doesn't work here explicitly, because God does not determine
the will of human beings.
We'll get there.
There's no way around this right his
argument against astrology in city of God makes it clear he did not he was not a
predesitorian in the Calvinist sense yeah remotely so he talks about so part of
what he's talking about is this context is what we would today call birth
Horoscopes. Yeah, yeah, you know, watch one of our colors brought up. Yeah, yeah.
the idea that if you're born under a particular sign,
then that kind of determines what we're talking about.
It's happening, et cetera.
Yeah, now we tend to talk about it
in terms of determining your personality,
but also the newspaper horoscopes.
On some level, it's your fate, right?
But ancient people, it's much more about fate.
It determines your fate.
Um, and so yeah.
But you know, my view is not the same as Rebecca Demorney or Elliott Cooled.
Clearly, clearly, or Michael Jackson, definitely not Michael Jackson.
You are not in fact a dead billionaire.
You have had no plastic surgery to my knowledge.
None none whatsoever.
Never broken any of my own bones.
So say the gust and points out so
practical things. Like how about twins? Yeah, why are they not, why do they not have the same feet?
Twins, yeah, who has say to Gus, it says are conceived at the same time and born near to one another.
And yet have different fates, different things happen with them. And even sometimes have different
personalities right and then he talks about birth or he talks about you know
There are children born to very wealthy families and very poor families on the same day,
at the same time, and relatively near each other.
And then being from a rich or poor family seems to be a lot more determinative of the course
of the rest of their life than their time and date of birth.
Yep.
So, St. Augustine was a Marxist.
QED.
We got to blame everything bad in the West on St. Augustine, don't we?
Like that's what I've heard.
That's the whole schnick.
Okay, so Marxism, St. Augustine's fault.
Well, it's all about spinal cord fluid.
Only a few people out there.
Oh, okay.
Okay.
I haven't achieved that level of initiation in the culture.
So I don't know about the spinal fluid.
Oh, you don't know about the spinal fluid?
No, I do know about the spinal fluid.
What else can I say?
I was going to say it's
I have to wait until we're done. We'll talk off the air about that one. I know exactly what you're talking about. Okay. Okay. Just give us K-Fabe. Come on.
Yeah.
And so
Zeta Gustin then answers the objection. Well, what about when they get things right?
Yeah. Doesn't it work sometimes?
Right. Does it work sometimes?
And this is another.
I've got some more rough news for you, Calvinist friends.
St. Augustine says, that's due to luck and chance.
What?
There's luck in both of which St. Augustine believes exist.
Yeah.
Yep.
Um,
so
uh,
now within this,
St. Augustine still has the idea he refers to the stars as powers.
He saw the idea that they're connected to it.
angelic beings, right? But he has this core problem with fatalism. And with the idea
that astrology for it to work would have to deny the freedom of the human will, he explicitly
says, say to us to explicitly says, in city of God five, that God, the omnipotent God,
Right, I'm nipping God works in the world and is a control sovereign control of all of
the powers, right? Meaning the heavenly bodies, the angels associated with them. He is in control of
but not all wills. So I'm saying Augustine explicitly says here that God does not control human
wills, or at least not all of them. We'll come back to that in a minute.
And it's...
So the picture that's saying Augustine paints here is, yes, God's energies, his activities
in the world. He is omnipotent. Right? He is omnipotent. And he acts within creation. Right?
But he does not.
override the human will. Therefore, there is contingency in the world based on the human
will. And therefore, astrology can't work.
So his whole argument against astrology basically denies the foundations of Calvinism.
Yes, it's based on the freedom of the human will.
So he says, yes, God's will does govern the movements in the heavens.
But you cannot use that to predict the future because of human will.
Humans cannot use that to predict the future.
He doesn't say anything about God and the future.
But let me clue you in on this.
St. Augustine was a Platonist, so he believes that God is outside of time.
Okay, so there is no future for God.
But so he's not talking about God's knowledge, but he's saying humans cannot foretell the
future.
Humans cannot know the future because of the contingency in the future produced by the
freedom of the human well.
That's that's just saying Augustin, man.
Yep, let's see the gun.
What can I say to you?
If you don't believe me, you can go look it up.
The rest of you have got.
So we also mentioned St. John Christophe.
The main critique we have from him.
Of astrology.
It's a little different because it's in a homily.
Right?
So like St. Augustine.
The confessions talks about in his own life.
about in his own life.
he had for a while in astrology and then why he said it aside.
City of God, he talks theologically about why astrology doesn't work.
St. John Chrysostom is in a homily trying to urge his hearers, his congregation,
not to get involved in practicing astrology.
So he's coming at it from a little different angle, right?
And the key thing, again, that St. John Chrysostom was...
to hammer on is the stars being angels, the stars being powers, right?
Angels being associated with them, right?
And that any independent power, any independent judgment,
any independent control of events of the world that you try to give to these
angelic beings for St.
Dr. Soss-Daburde Fakdo taking that control away from God himself.
You're saying this is not God doing this.
Yes.
This is this other being.
It's basically like what Philo said just you know for 100 years before
Chrysostom.
Yes.
Very similar.
Right.
And so he wants to hammer on and in context.
So he's he's talking about this in the context of preaching about the Magi and the star.
Right.
any. He doesn't want in St. Matthew's gospel. He doesn't want his congregation.
to say, oh, okay, astrology is cool because the match I did astrology had found Christ, right?
And so again, he's hammering on the star of Bethlehem as an angel, right? It's a messenger of God
that God used in that instance, right? To send this message to those people,
this is not about astrology the way the pagans practice it, right? That's sort of his his
So going back to the question we had at the beginning of this third half,
why is there then this sudden shift with Christianity?
Right. Why is why we've now argued that
The core element of Christian theology that makes astrology not work that makes it a problem is this idea of the freedom of the will
But why is that a thing that that particularly enters into
theology with Christianity per se
as opposed to
preceding forms of second-temporal Judaism for example. Yeah
Yeah, I mean, so.
something shifts. Yeah. Yeah. And so there is within the second temple Jewish view,
like us, phyllo outlined it, even within that there's a kind of subtle determinism in there.
In that even if you understand it the way phyllo does that whatever the stars may say about
the future, it's God saying it about the future.
That's still a human being able to derive certain knowledge of particular future events,
which is essentially divination, but also requires a certain amount of determinism.
Right. And so the key here is the understanding of the human will that
enters into Christian thought and understanding through the concept of nature,
which enters Christian understanding through essentially Saint Paul.
So we've talked about this a couple of times before on the show, but
the Greek word feces that we translate nature does not occur in the Old Testament in Greek.
It's just, it's not used.
It's maybe used once in an odd way in an appendix to the Old Testament, depending on what kind of Orthodox Christian you are.
But otherwise, it is not used in the Old Testament.
Let's say Paul uses it a lot, and it gets used a couple of other times in the New Testament as well.
And...
We've talked about how, for St. Paul nature, human nature in particular is one.
All humans share one human nature, which is the big innovation and how he uses it as opposed to how Greek philosophy had used it.
Greek philosophy had used nature largely to talk about the concept of what we would call heredity.
Right, so different humans had different natures for Aristotle.
people who are by nature slaves and people who are by nature rulers and people who are by nature warriors and etc.
There were better and worse classes of people and nature was an individual thing. It was your individual set of inherited traits was your individual nature.
whereas for Saint Paul, as he says at the Aereopagus, from one man, God created all the man.
on the face of the earth. Right? So all humans share one nature. And that nature is represents an
orientation of humanity for him that one human nature, for St. Paul, is in certain ways synonymous with
the image of God, meaning that that nature is not just a static.
thing, right? It's not just some quality or set of qualities that all humans possess
that makes them human, but it is an orientation in a particular direction, right, of a human.
So, to use an example within the Greek philosophical use, and Acorn has the nature
of an oak tree. And so sort of the purpose, the tellos, the end, the purpose, the fulfillment
of what it is to be an acorn is to grow into a full grown oak tree. That's what it's aimed
at. So for humans who are made of the image of God, human nature is that we are all aimed
at becoming God.
We are all aimed at becoming like God.
Yeah, this is the basis or the conform to the image of Christ.
This language is all over St. Paul, right?
This is theosis, right?
The full measure, right, to be perfect, to be complete.
The likeness of Christ, right?
All of this language in St. Paul, right?
That is what every human being is aimed at.
is the potential of every human being.
that is what every human being was created to do.
Okay?
Will then, as understood within Christian theology,
for all of its history in the East,
and still by St. Augustine in the West,
the will is directly connected to your nature.
Right, so, yeah.
understand philosophically the idea of motion and change. So we have this acorn. It's nature,
part of its nature is that it's tell us is to become an oak tree. For it to become a full
grown oak tree, it's going to have to grow and change a lot. It's going to have to increase
exponentially in size. Right? It is going to have to undergo all kinds of processes and transformations,
Right, over the course of its lifespan, right?
in order to reach that tell us if it does.
And yet, Acorns do this all the time
without some human doing something to them.
There's not some outside being,
some other being who comes
and does something to the Acorn to turn it into an oak tree.
Rather, there is this internal life,
this in.
internal drive
That causes it to seek an absorbed nourishment
Right to grow to live to be transformed
That internal drive that internal movement
Say Max of us talks about the will in terms of movement internal movement, right? That is what we call the will
So the human well is the internal
the internal push to grow to be transformed, right, to be spiritually nourished, to be transformed into the likeness of Christ.
Right? That's what an every human possesses that will. That is the will that is connected to every human nature.
Okay, but that will just like with the eight.
not every very corn grows into an oak tree.
Yeah.
Right. There are things that can come in and stunt that development.
They can stop it at some point along the chain that can kill it.
Right. Before it achieves that.
And so,
again, the traditional Christian understanding, including the
understanding of saying at gustin is that sin.
corruption, death. These things are obstacles that obstruct the will, that stop the human
well from developing in the direction of the fullness of the lightness of Christ. Therefore,
Salvation, the human will is freed.
Right?
Freed not to make choices.
That's a whole other thing.
It's a whole other thing that we won't talk about right now.
Freed to push forward toward what it was created to be.
To push toward perfection, to push toward maturity.
Right?
It's freed from that, to go in that one direction.
So when...
Sin Augustine talks about our human will being bound by sin. He doesn't mean that somehow
We've lost the ability to choose to do a good thing
Yeah
Right
We know that's not true
Atheists and heathens do good things all the time
They help someone in need they show love to someone
happens every day.
Good.
they were able to do that. But what they're not able to do, right, without the
transforming grace of God, is become like Christ. Is experience salvation is
theosis. That's what they're not able to do without that. You could do plenty
nice things you can do plenty of good things.
So, for St. Augustine, for all of the Church fathers, right, when the will is freed from those obstacles,
right, from those obstructions, right, from those things that, that goes like a white force that
to go in the wrong direction, right, or lead it to go in the wrong direction. When it's free from that,
then naturally our human will.
follows and participates in and is guided by God's will. This is what say to
Guston Mett when he said God does not grant all wills. Right, only those
which have been freed. Right, only those which have been freed from sin. That's
That's what's meant by a free will.
And so Christianity, right, the key problem with practicing astrology as a mode of divination
is that Christianity is an ethos of freedom.
And the practice of astrology is divination.
is it ethos of determinism, fatalism of enslavement?
to the elemental powers that govern this press of evil age.
Right? It is an ethos that brings one under the control of those powers, which is bondage
and slavery and not actual freedom.
And so it closing, say Paul says something about this, and Hebrews chapter 12,
I'm going to go to the
first one.
Which I'm pulling up on my
screen right now.
You're the one who's supposed to
prepare for these things.
I know.
I know you just walk on.
Long ago.
At many others that's he was one.
There we go.
I need he was 12.
12 first one.
Yes.
Therefore, brethren since we are
I'm going to just go ahead and
read through the whole book.
for our sins we are so-
I mean, yeah, yeah, I mean, I'm the little versus since we're surrounded by so great a cloud of witnesses.
Let us also lay aside every weight and sin which clings so closely and let us run with endurance, the race that is set before us.
Yeah.
You know, one of the thoughts that occurred to me, especially here at the end and talking about freedom,
is
I think, I mean, most people, at least most Christians, are not engaging in divination by means
of astrology.
So it's probably not that particular sin is not something that most people are tempted
towards or find themselves engaged in.
I mean, although, I mean, you know, this is going on.
This is not just all in the past.
But one of the big struggles I think that a lot of people have.
is probably all of us have on some level is our experience of what sin is. Right. So St. Paul
here in Hebrews 121 describes it as a weight.
Sin which clings closely says.
And I think a lot of times people experience this as inner flaws. Right.
Right, like, well, there's something
wrong with me. It's just who I am, whatever. And you can see how that's kind of related
to this astrological stuff. Like, well, well, you know, I'm just a, I'm just a Pisces.
I'm just an Aquarius. I'm just a Virgo, you know, whatever. Which is just another way
of saying, you know, who I am, what I do has been determined. There's nothing I can do about it.
And this also gets
It's a problem when considering evil in the world, what's wrong with people, why are
people like this?
But the element that's left out of a lot of this is an element that we have discussed
of course many, many times of the last five plus years of this podcast, which is that there
other spiritual beings on the field in play.
particularly the dark demonic powers, what they are doing when we listen to them, when we participate with them, what they are doing is putting us in bondage.
They're putting weights on us. They're clinging to us, you know, to use St. Paul's language here in Hebrews 12-1.
And the object
then of being a Christian is to become free of that, right? So that we don't have them
dragging us down. We call what it is we're doing, we call what it is we're participating
in salvation. And that the word salvation has become such a sort of technical religious
term that I think often its literal sense is lost for a lot of people. Salvation means
to be.
rescued to be saved from something, to be pulled away from something. And it's not only an eternal fate of
the lake of fire that we are saved from. That's just kind of the final act, so to speak. We're being saved
from the power of the evil one,
we're being saved from the influence of the dark powers.
And it's there working in us that is sin.
And it's our cooperation with them
that is when we sin.
And when you understand that this problem of evil
in the world is a problem of evil beings,
evil spiritual beings in the world,
then I think that the project in a lot of ways
becomes much clearer.
It is a project, the project of Christianity is an exorcistic project.
It's casting out demonic forces.
But it's also, of course, about synergizing with God.
It's about cooperating with God, about working together with God, receiving through our faithfulness,
that which is grace accomplishes in us as a free gift.
It's exactly what you see at the beginning of normal.
Orthodox baptismal service where you're turning your back on the dark powers and you're
turning towards the Lord Jesus Christ. You're disillining yourself with Satan and all his
service, all his pride, all his pomp, whatever translation you're listening to, and aligning
yourself with Christ, participating in Christ.
a lot of the way that we see the world, at least here in the United States and
I know we have some people listening from other places too, but maybe so maybe you're
affected by this, I don't know.
But a lot of the way that we see the world is we often have this sense of like, well that's
just the way things are.
That's just who I am.
That's just the way it is.
A fatalistic point of view.
I can never be more than what I am.
I can never be other than what I am.
I mean, we see this on the popular culture now too.
right? There is often this kind of like this is the this is the nature of cancel culture,
right? Cancel culture is all about destroying someone else because of course repentance is not a
thing. But repentance is a thing. Change is possible. Not just for me, but for you know, those people,
whoever those people are, the bad people doing bad things. But God is not willing that any
parish, Christ died for us for us while we were yet sinners, meaning that he believes
in change.
He makes change possible.
And so what we learn from this examination of astrology is not just, you know, don't do
divination, obviously, okay, don't do divination.
But also we learn that as Father Stephen just said, the goal is freedom.
Christianity is based on human freedom.
Freedom to become what it is that God has made us to be,
to lay aside all the weight so that we can grow so we can become truly
sons of God equal to the angels.
That's the Lord Jesus himself said.
And so, far from being a kind of just weird esoteric subject,
this expression of astrology in the ancient
world and holy scriptures and of course Christianity's response to it.
It actually goes right to the heart of who we are, what it is we're trying to
accomplish as Christians and what it is that Jesus did for us. So that's those
are some of my big takeaways from this.
So relatedly, let me first offer as proof of my love for you the listener that I
I am giving the last of my voice to this
broadcast this evening as you could probably hear.
Goodbye now at least.
So yeah, related to what Father Andrew was saying, right?
I think we underestimate the degree to which
many, if not most of us,
have given other people control over our life.
And, you know, for most of you, again, as Father Andrew said, for most of you, that's probably not an astrologer, right?
Pretty sure Nancy Reagan isn't listening from beyond the grave.
So most of you are not making all of your life decisions based on what an astrologer tells you per se.
But
There are a lot of us who have heard voices could be from one or both of our parents
siblings co-workers schoolmates
bosses
Sort of the the general run of society in which we found ourselves
That have told us
Surely as an astrologer would
What we're supposed to be like.
who are supposed to be, how we're supposed to act, what kind of career we should pursue
and why, what it is that gives us value as a human being, what our purpose is or should be
down to some time details of what we ought to do.
And we've taken that and we've internalized it. And a lot of us have internalized it to the point
that even if the parent who was saying
it to us has been dead for years or we haven't seen the teacher who sent it to us in decades
or the schoolmates are scattered to the four winds living in all parts of the country
we've never seen them since.
Whoever it is, that voice is still now inside of us reiterating the same things.
And one of two things happens.
we have this idea of what our destiny or fate should be, how our life should be, what
things should be like. Either we achieve it, we actually do those things. We slave away
for that voice, whoever's voice it is, to make happen whatever it's saying we're supposed
to make happen to make our
life are supposed to make it.
And then when we've done that, we are profoundly unhappy.
We are profoundly lonely and isolated.
The things that God promises us like love, joy, peace,
kind of as good are far from us.
Even though we've done all the things
we were supposed to do.
become the kind of person we were supposed to be.
Or, as is probably more common,
we worked a toil to try to do all those things that voice said we should do,
to try and be what it said we should be, and we haven't achieved it.
We haven't achieved that destiny.
And that then means that we're worthless.
That then means that we're garbage. That means that all those efforts, our whole life, has been a waste.
Because it didn't turn out the way it was supposed to turn out.
We didn't achieve the things we were supposed to achieve. We didn't get the things we were supposed to have.
And we either on one side get angry at the world for not being the way we thought.
it should be, and we become destructive, or we internalize it and we become self-destructive.
We may not directly harm ourselves, but we'll do it passive aggressively.
We'll do things that we know will ruin our health. We'll do things that we know will
ruin our relationships in our life in general.
And so for me.
The big part of the message tonight is that Christ has come to set us free, not only
from astrology as but one example, but from all of those voices, all of those powers, all
of those influences that we've allowed to enslave us for our entire lives.
Because whatever destiny they are proposing to you, whatever career,
however much wealth, whatever happiness in marriage and family, whatever those things they were claiming
where your destiny and you needed to achieve or you needed to have or you needed to do,
those were, those are small fry, those are pathetic compared to becoming like Christ.
That is small potatoes.
That's being like Esau and selling your birthright for a bowl of soup.
Even if you achieve it.
And you can see how happy Esau was after the soup was gone.
Careful filthy felt.
Christ came because God wants you to flourish.
He wants you to grow.
He wants you to live.
He wants you to live a life that's full of love, joy, peace, patience, kindness, goodness,
faithfulness, gentleness, self-control.
once.
to become like Christ, he wants you to live that way eternally.
And he came to open up that path for you.
The incarnation is what changed everything.
That's what brought our human nature back to life.
That's what set our wheel free.
And in favor of that, none of those voices have anything to promise us in comparison.
Nothing to offer.
We only try to drag us back down.
So the purpose of this episode tonight was not to tell you, hey, when you get to that page
to the news.
paper like any of you read newspapers, but let's pretend, don't you dare read the horoscopes.
Don't you dare crack open and read that fortune cookie? Dividation is evil.
The purpose of this episode is so that we have hopefully one more thing to thank God for.
that he set us free not only from all
the demonic powers on this earth, but even from our fellow human beings, their expectations
and demands on us, and even the expectations and demands that we put on ourselves. And
that's what it means to be truly free.
Well, that's our show for tonight, everybody.
Thank you very much for listening.
If you didn't happen to get through to us live,
we'd still like to hear from you.
You can email us, LordofSpirits.nfate.com.
You can send us a message through our Facebook page.
You can also leave us a voice mail at SpeakPipe.com,
slash LordofSpirits.
If you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity
or you need help finding a parish,
go to Orthodoxintro.org.
And join us for our live broadcast
on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month
at 7 p.m. Eastern, 4 p.m. Pacific.
Well, the year starts.
coming and they don't stop coming.
Fed to the rules and I hit the ground running.
If you're on Facebook, you could follow our page.
You can join our discussion group and please give us a review
of rating so other people can connect to the soap
and make sure that you share it directly with a friend who
is going to benefit from it.
And finally, be sure to go to htfaith.com
Stroke Support to help make sure we and lots of other AFR
podcasters stay on the air.
Didn't make sense not to live for fun.
Your brain gets smart, but your head gets dumb.
Thank you, good night. God bless you.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen De Young,
a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I be held, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne, and the beasts, and the elders, and the number of them was
10,000 times 10,000 and thousands of thousands seeing with a lot
voice worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom and
strength and honor and glory and blessing. Revelation chapter 5